### Contact

www.linkedin.com/in/ stevehoffmanchicago (LinkedIn)

### Top Skills

Amazon Web Services (AWS)

Docker

**Distributed Systems** 

### Languages

English (Native or Bilingual)

### **Publications**

Combatting DNS Exfiltration in AWS CHUG Meetup - Apache Flume: a streaming data transport framework

Minor Appearance in Stash Product Case Study

flAWS.cloud Walkthrough at AWS Chicago Meetup

**Enabling Microservices at Orbitz** 

#### **Patents**

High-persistence display circuit and method to therefor

Booking engine for booking airline tickets on multiple host environments

Method and apparatus for dispersed storage memory device selection

Method and apparatus for dispersed storage memory device selection

Memory device utilization in a dispersed storage network

# Steve Hoffman

Engineering Leader at DoorDash

Greater Chicago Area

# Summary

Software and Computer Engineer with over 30 years of experience ranging from the first GSM cellular handsets to the development/ launches of large scale distributed systems & websites, public and private cloud infrastructure automation, docker on mesos, and many things AWS with a brief jaunt into software storage appliances and hadoop/big data.

I currently work on infrastructure automation, AWS cloud infrastructure, continuous delivery pipelines, and docker on Amazon ECS.

I like working with smart motivated people I can learn from and who can learn from me.

## Experience

DoorDash

Senior Principal Engineer October 2020 - Present (4 years 4 months)

Chicago, Illinois, United States

Journera

Senior Principal Engineer

August 2016 - October 2020 (4 years 3 months)

Chicago, IL

Founding Team Enterprise Architect for Operations and Security hired to build a green-field streaming platform for a business to business travel data exchange/marketplace.

- Worked with CSO to design and build dual account, multiple VPC AWS network for separation of duties across teams
- Led DevOps team of three
- Daily coordination with Enterprise Architect for Development to build greenfield application platform including:

- \* immutable infrastructure EC2 servers and services
- \* Golang docker apps deployed w/ ECS that communicate by HTTP, SQS or Kinesis
- \* common logging and metrics framework using fluentd, logz.io and honeycomb.io
  - \* common secrets management based on credstash
  - \* Concourse and CircleCl Cl/CD pipelines
- Infrastructure as code principles including:
  - \* terraform for servers, networking, IAM roles, and docker services
  - ★ packer for EC2 AMIs
- Security and privacy by design, adhering to least privileged access for applications and employees
- Initial data science platform based on AWS Redshift, Glue, Firehoses to S3
   Data Lake
- Managed the AWS budget and worked with finance on annual projections, quarterly updates and spending reductions where possible.
- Assisted in the development of technology that led to patent #10,326,742
   Cryptographically enforced data exchange

### Raise.com

Senior Principal Engineer January 2016 - August 2016 (8 months)

Joined DevOps team to assist microservices/Docker migration of legacy Rails application.

- Assisted in Agile rollout to teams
- Re-designed the production network within Amazon's AWS from the ground up to maximize data protection and customer transactions utilizing AWS Best Practices and Least Privileged principles
- Implemented Mesos cluster for ad-hoc jobs and ephemeral Dockerized Jenkins workers in new Production network.
- Participated in M&A due diligence for the acquisition of Slide

#### Orbitz Worldwide

Senior Principal Engineer March 2010 - January 2016 (5 years 11 months)

Upon Steve's return to Orbitz, he drove the standardization of Hadoop usage including:

Repeatable installs using Puppet configuration management

- Automated user deployments to pre-production and production environments (including ITSM-compliant change ticketing)
- HBase on HDFS
- Data ingestion using rsyslog/Flume/MapReduce
- Automated partitioning of external Hive tables to minimize Administrator involvement.

During this time, he authored two editions of his first book (see publications).

His next project focused on infrastructure as code during a company-wide private-cloud virtualization effort including:

- chef server provisioning
- cookbook/environment/role management and release procedures through git.
- automatic synchronization between git and multiple chef environments.
- custom knife integration to create a PaaS style command line tool integrating cloud server provisioning and bootstrapping.

Steve's most recent project work involves Orbitz's next generation platform based on Docker microservices running on Apache Mesos in multiple environments including:

- multi-master Mesos and companion services via Chef automation.
- multi-master Marathon and Chronos for long-term and scheduled Docker applications
- Jenkins/Mesos inegration which formed the foundation for a human-free release pipeline (See DockerCon 2015 presentation links)
- Jenkins/Mesos plugin setup and patches for ephemeral Docker-ized Jenkins slaves (See MesosCon 2015 presentation links)

#### Cleversafe

Senior Software Architect

October 2007 - February 2010 (2 years 5 months)

During Steve's time at Cleversafe, he built the company's first Kickstart based installer (plug-in/boot installer via USB/DVD) which allowed them to launch an appliance based product in minutes - replacing their hand-installed play books.

Next he worked with the centralized manager team to develop a secure and centralized Yum-based upgrade mechanism for (potentially) geographically dispersed appliances. This secure solution also included centralized logging, monitoring and alerting via the in-house management platform.

Steve also developed the first HA solution for the Accessor using linux-ha as well as alternative service stacks including NFS, AFP and CIFS (also HA where possible).

G2 SwitchWorks
Senior Software Developer
June 2005 - September 2007 (2 years 4 months)

Building on his experience at Orbitz, Steve worked on several integrations with travel partners such as AirTran airlines into the G2 platform.

### Orbitz

Principal Engineer
June 2000 - June 2005 (5 years 1 month)

As the second developer hired to build orbitz.com internally, Steve integrated multiple parts from consultants building the web and booking engine layers to a successful launch. As the development team grew internally, he worked in several areas across the platform.

Later, Steve spearheaded the drive towards service-oriented-artchitecture based on Java's Jini technology - which is still in some use today (See JavaOne 2004 Presentation links).

### Zefer

Software Engineer 1999 - June 2000 (1 year) Internet Consulting

Misc projects including a 4 months overseas Internet Strategy engagement for Zuellig Pharmaceuticals (zuelligpharma.com). Based in Hong-Kong, traveled to Taiwan, Singapore, Kuala Lumpur, Malaysia and the Philippines to meet directly with customers.

Neoglyphics Media Corporation Software Engineer/Manager August 1996 - 1999 (3 years) Internet Consulting

Development of multiple web presences during early years of the Internet (precrash) Developed a C-CGI based "build your own website" for launch of ameritech.net (Ameritech's first home internet service offering.

Lead developer/architect for Fisher Scientific's first e-commerce website (fishersci.com). Written using Java Servlets and JSPs it served up tens of thousands of products previous only purchased through pre-Internet channels. The biggest challenge being it had to use the same database as their print catalog being developed by another firm.

Lead developer/architect for ebdirect.com, an Internet startup which directly sold insurance benefits to small businesses via the Internet. Implemented using Java EJBs, Servlets and JSPs.

Manager for 1/5 of development which included performance and compensation reviews.

Motorola

6 years 3 months

Software Engineer I
December 1991 - August 1996 (4 years 9 months)

GSM Core Software - European Products Division

Developed the first GSM handsets for Europe's emerging cellular telephone standard. Written in C++, made heavy use of Object-Oriented programming to support multiple handset models/types. Later enhanced to support graphical displays for Chinese character support as GSM spread to the Asic-Pac region.

Software Engineer II

June 1990 - December 1991 (1 year 7 months)

Land Mobile Products Group - Private Trunked Radio Division

Development and support of embedded software for trunked radio base stations.

McSoftware Software Developer June 1983 - August 1985 (2 years 3 months) Glenview, IL

Developed school bookstore program which was in use for 3 years for school district 255 (approx. 4000 high school students). Written in Pascal and ran

on the Apple II, data was stored to floppy disks during transactions and batch uploaded later to central database for reconciliation.

Developed Macintosh based test reader software using serially connected Scantron test reader. Written in Pascal on Macintosh, was sold commercially for about 5 years. 4D database used to pre-print class forms from central database. Raw score data later analyzed by custom Macintosh application to produce statistics and graphs.

### Education

DePaul University

MS, Computer Science - Telecom · (1992 - 1994)

University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign
Bachelor of Science - BS, Computer Engineering · (1986 - 1990)